<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Shastri&#x27;s Blogs</title>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://theshastri.xyz/blogs/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://theshastri.xyz/blogs"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2023-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://theshastri.xyz/blogs/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Why should you need switch from an IDE to PDE right now</title>
        <published>2023-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://theshastri.xyz/blogs/blog/why-should-you-need-switch-from-an-ide-to-pde-right-now/"/>
        <id>https://theshastri.xyz/blogs/blog/why-should-you-need-switch-from-an-ide-to-pde-right-now/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://theshastri.xyz/blogs/blog/why-should-you-need-switch-from-an-ide-to-pde-right-now/">&lt;p&gt;In my following article(s), I want to tell you why i switchedfrom 
an &lt;strong&gt;IDE&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (Integrated Development Environment) to a &lt;strong&gt;PDE&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (Personal Development Environment)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started programming when i was 16 and i was the script kiddo (still same &amp;lt;3).
I used VSCode and windows everyday for programming . The junky bloated electron
app always ate my memmory and made my programming sessions worse.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, I saw some guy&#x27;s YouTube video on his workflow setup. The way he navigated
through his code and tabs just made me go wow. But i had no idea about what these 
guys are using except that, I knew that he was using linux. Later i get to know that 
he was using something called vim and which is a efficient text editor and it focuses 
more on make coding and writing faster by eliminating the need of mouse. 
I planned to give it a try because of my potato pc and VScode.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to be honest, I was a heavy mouse user. I heavily relied on the mouse
for switching tabs, browsing the internet, and programming. Switching between
tabs in windows and finding the right one was the worst. It felt like a nightmare. I had
to decide where to go from the list of applications when I press ALT+TAB. 
Also I didn&#x27;t have any previous experience with Linux other than just using it
inside a virtual machine for 30 minutes. The next day, I installed Linux Mint 
as my primary operating system and started my Linux journey.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to today, here are the major changes that happened to me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1 Text Editing &lt;&#x2F;h2&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;theshastri.s3.us-west-1.amazonaws.com&#x2F;noevim.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
Speaking of programming in VSCode, I didn&#x27;t remember many shortcuts,
except for Ctrl+P, Ctrl+F, and Ctrl+Shift+F. I know there are a few 
more, but the editor itself didn&#x27;t compel me to use them. I was so lazy 
that I even opened the definition of a function by clicking the function 
name with Ctrl pressed, rather than just reading the docs and pressing F12.
I know that this sounds like a real skill issue but most of the people i know 
using VScode are same as mine. They dont learn these shortcuts when they can 
use mouse
&lt;p&gt;I switched from VSCode to Vim and can confidently say that Vim has become an
integral part of my programming toolkit. The initial learning curve was steep,
but the investment in mastering Vim&#x27;s commands paid off exponentially.
&lt;code&gt;Tmux + Treesitter + telescope + harpoon + LSP &lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is all you need to get started. It
made my programming more fun, and it&#x27;s nice to have a little hobby of setting up
your own configs, plugins, etc. Also, most importantly, I can now say &amp;quot;I USE
NEOVIM BTW&amp;quot; to my friends 🗿 (Oh wait i dont have one to say that)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;br&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;br&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2 Window Management &lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;theshastri.s3.us-west-1.amazonaws.com&#x2F;dwm.png&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
The window manager is—just like the name describes—a window manager. It controls
the positioning of windows, their look and feel, etc. I use dwm, which has
transformed the way I interact with applications and manage windows. Here, I
follow a general rule while launching applications. Like Firefox goes to the 1st
tab. Similarly, Discord in 8th, etc. So there is no unnecessary mess going on. I
know exactly where I should go, no more decision-making from a large list of
applications.
&lt;&#x2F;br&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;br&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3 Browsing &lt;&#x2F;h2&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;theshastri.s3.us-west-1.amazonaws.com&#x2F;archenjoyer.png&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
I use Firefox browser with the Vimium plugin enabled. It provides keyboard
shortcuts for navigation and control in the spirit of Vim, which also increases
my muscle memory with Vim 😉. I highly recommend this plugin for those who wish
to jump to Vim from VSCode or other editors. But it is just a plugin; it has
many limitations. I strongly believe that a new browser incorporating proper Vim
motions has the potential to become a highly successful product.
&lt;&#x2F;br&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;br&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>My First Blog</title>
        <published>2023-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://theshastri.xyz/blogs/blog/myfirstblog/"/>
        <id>https://theshastri.xyz/blogs/blog/myfirstblog/</id>
        
        <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s about 1:28 AM, and I&#x27;m writing my very first blog. For the past month, I&#x27;ve been thinking about
starting a blog, but I kept procrastinating and wasting my time. I knew I was wasting my time, but I
just couldn&#x27;t find the motivation to begin. It felt like I was stuck, unable to start. I tried
learning some technologies, but nothing changed. And today, for God&#x27;s sake, somehow I got the
motivation to start this. Right now, I&#x27;ve almost covered the technical part of it. </summary>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
